[Music]
do
hello again everybody very nice to see
you all uh welcome to the 70th episode
of ask a budget
only two more episodes to go in this
year so let's have some fun
all right let's see who all is there
today uh first of all let me explain uh
today is a live chat session as i'm sure
you know i'll be taking questions only
from the live chat so if you have
questions that i have not answered
before
keep them ready and i will hopefully
pick up your question i know there will
be thousands of questions i'll pick
uh as many as i can
right so uh let me see whole is there i
can see krish pratik sports only cyan
roy
and many more people
great to see you all great to see you
all i hope you're doing well
okay guys girls ladies gentlemen let's
have your questions and i shall answer
answer them um
all right let's see what all we have
here
do we have any questions
do we have any questions uh
praveen says how to be motivated if you
well how to be motivated you need to
have a big goal
if you have a big goal in life
you have the motivation to achieve it
and that big goal has to be something
that comes from within you not someone
something that someone imposes on you
and forces you to do you have a boring
nine-to-five job
you're forced to do things that you may
not really enjoy
right
in that case where's the motivation
you're just doing it because you earn
money from there and that's why you have
to do it but if there is
a big goal that you have
a big goal maybe 10 years down the line
you want to achieve that then you have
the motivation right from inside because
it's a goal you set for yourself then
you're motivated so find your purpose in
life first understand yourself you
cannot find a purpose in life unless you
first understand who you are
and most people unfortunately go through
life without ever
understanding themselves
so do some self-introspection it takes
time
takes time
but you have to understand yourself you
have to understand
what lies within
right
what your values are
what kind of a world you would like to
see long term and then try to make it
happen so that's the kind of thing that
leads to motivation once you have an
objective you don't have any problem of
motivation
it's always people who are unmotivated
are people who lack an objective and
that typically happens when you're very
young and you don't know you don't
understand life you don't understand
yourself you don't understand the world
so that's why you have to understand the
world you have to that's why it's
important to read history understand
culture and then also understand
yourself then you will understand where
where you stand where the world is going
what is right with the world what is
wrong with the world then you can have
some objective for yourself that this is
what i want to do to shape the world in
a certain way and then there will be no
issue of motivation so that's the kind
of thing you need to do
okay
okay some more questions i can see hi
hello everyone yeah let's see let's go
down and let's find some question
um
uh okay let's see
i have already spoken about baba ravel
in the past so
you can check that out
um
okay mahul says if we find out an
intelligent life form outside of our
solar system
then what effects on religions and their
effects on our society i don't see any
effect on religion
uh if we discover an intelligent life
form outside of our solar system it is
alarm bells because they could be more
intelligent than us and maybe they would
want to harm us
you always have to assume the worst when
you see when you're walking down the
road
3am in the morning everything is dark
outside and you see some stranger coming
towards you
what do you do you go and say hey
brother how is it going or do you be
careful
you have to assume the worst when you're
in an unknown place in complete darkness
middle of the night and you see a
stranger approaching you have to take
all possible precautions
the same goes for it discovering
intelligent life forms anywhere else we
have never
been so
uh fortunate i would say is to having
have this having ever discovered another
species
beyond our planet beyond our solar
system if we do it has to be with
extreme caution we have to approach
everything with extreme caution first of
all we should not advertise our location
that hey guys hello listen to us we are
here this is our location don't do that
please don't do that but we are doing it
that's not a very good idea
so uh but if we discover any such
intelligent species outside of our solar
system
what effect will it have on religions
uh
i don't see any effect on religions
religions
the abrahamic religions are
extraordinarily dogmatic it's all in the
book and nothing outside so the book is
is not going to change whatever books
they they follow each religion has one
book
one one
major book central book so that is never
going to change and therefore there will
be no change in the religion when it
comes to other cultures etc well
if you look at
the dharmic religions dharma so-called
religions dharmic
continuum the dharmic practices the
dharmic civilization in that case we
have always i mean our ancestors have
always believed that there are multiple
locus right multiple multiple spheres of
existence and all that so that
essentially says that there are worlds
beyond our own over our earth our solar
system and therefore it's not going to
change anything about that it's it's
gonna be like yeah we already knew this
so that's the kind of thing there is
it's more about technology and defense
and all that that we need to look at it
will not really change religion what
effect will it have on society well some
people will go
in panic mode some people will be
hysteric some people will say oh let's
welcome them with garlands aliens and so
on so forth
it depends you know it's going to have a
wide range of effects on society
okay
anish kulkarni says why do sadhus and
rishis have long hair in bed whereas
monks are always clean shaved
and we find more monks in buddhism than
hinduism and vice versa for southern
rishis why so
listen there is no hinduism there is no
buddhism it's the same thing
and hinduism was was more or less
destroyed in india
all the monasteries
all the
universities everything was wiped out
and therefore this practice disappeared
in other countries
thailand burma china korea japan etc
the more uh
the practices continued which no longer
continued inside india and over there
for whatever reason because of
historical uh
because of the chronology
uh they were at the time more influenced
by ideas that are now known as now now
uh
categorized as buddhist ideas even
though there are clear elements of
overall dharmic practices including what
is called hinduism in there
so that's why you see these monks
continuing the same traditions that were
prevalent in india
in these other countries and they are
all wearing uh those saffron ropes
everything which even dharmic all even
hindus wore right and where
so but now it is categorized as buddhism
if you go to thailand yeah they do
follow the precepts of the buddha but
they also
follow
they also worship lord shiva lord ganesh
and various other lord vishnu and so on
so it's wrong to call it buddhism it's
wrong to call it anything it's just
dharma
so
we also had the same thing in hinduism
right what we call hinduism it's just
that it's no longer prevalent in india
it's been destroyed our culture has been
destroyed and uprooted
and irati get eradicated from our land
and that's why we feel that only
buddhists have this thing because
today's academics and media everyone
they call those practices buddhist
practices it's not the case these are
dharmic practices in those buddhist
jains everybody has
has had monk hood and all that right
so it's not because hinduism has been
destroyed in india you may not realize
it you may not realize it because you
are all living in a la la land hinduism
has been destroyed in india
right
you are living in an enslaved state
whether you realize it or not india is
not a free country india is still under
foreign occupation whether you realize
it or not so hinduism has been
disordered in india all the ancient
practices has have been wiped out and
that's why it looks like whatever
happens abroad is all buddhist and it
was never there in hinduism so
that sort of thing that is not the case
now about long hair and beard see when
you're a monk
it means you're a youngster you're a
student you are being initiated into the
long grueling practice
of
of of being a
an aesthetic of spending your entire
life in contemplation and study
into the scholarly life it's a totally
different kind of life yeah so when you
are a monk you are being initiated into
this and you have to observe
very strict discipline
because only then will you learn
how to uh go higher
in this in this line in this in this
line of work which is the scholarly line
of work the uh the
uh yeah so that's what it is so that's
why when you are a monk you have to uh
observe extreme discipline and you are
told what to do so that you learn
quickly instead of trying to find out on
your own so you're told what to do you
are told to live a certain kind of life
in which there is absolute discipline
you shave off your head
your hair your hair you shave off your
beard everything you wear suffering
robes you wake up at a particular time
you do certain things at certain times
and it's complete regimented life and
it's a lot of discipline a lot of study
and all that and serving the serving the
master serving the monastery the
university wherever you
are and so on so forth so that's how it
is
but
once you are past a certain stage as a
monk i suppose you would uh
want to go into the forest and
contemplate or or move away from society
go to a forest and
and write whatever you want to write
because you now have the ideas and all
in that case you don't have the time to
shave and to cut your hair and all that
because your entire focus entire
existence is focused on whatever work
you're trying to produce
so in the past you had these rishes
sadhus etc would go off into forests
would go off into the mountains spend a
few years there and forget everything
else and just work and and write their
great works whatever
it all added up and contributed to the
enormous corpus of literature of indian
civilization and similarly you find
people everywhere in the world who go
off into this this self-imposed
exile or hiatus for instance isaac
newton is known to have disappeared for
ten years or so while he was writing his
principia mata mithika and uh albert
einstein also disappeared for 10 years
while he was
while he was formulating the theory of
general relativity it was a big struggle
so that's how it is
so once you are done with the initiation
into this work and into this lifestyle
then you can go off and do whatever you
want and most people actually do not go
and produce some great work so they
remain in the monastery and they
remained clean shaven and and bald
headed headed and all that so it all
depends the sadhus and rishis that we
have that we had in the past they used
to be exceptional people riches
especially
and so on
so i expect that even rishi who would
have long hair and a beard when he or
she he was a youngster or she was when
yeah it's a male thing beard so when he
was a youngster he would also have had
to shave off and
shave off the hair the hair as well
that's how it goes so that i hope
explains in short in brief
what this is about
okay
says do you think one person who is as
influential as hitler
and intelligent as chanakya can change
the face of the world of of the can
change the face of india on the world
level well i would never want to speak
out about adolf hitler that guy
destroyed his country he ended up
destroying his country and that guy was
a monster he killed so many people that
is not the way to do things but
unfortunately that's how things work in
the world whether we like it or not
i would never consider adolf hitler to
be any kind of hero
but yes he was somebody who did matter
who did shape the world as we know it so
yes he is one of the important figures
in history in the at least in the 20th
century
so what will it see uh
change the face of india on the world
level what does that mean you mean the
impression of india or the actual
uh
internal uh
power structure of india or the
level of hard power of india i i don't
care what people think about india
it does matter to some extent but
everything will change once india
becomes a stronger country with greater
hard power like i've always said in the
past
if you want people to respect you you
must first make them fear you you have
to first develop the economic muscle and
the military muscle and then you
use it for good don't use it for bad but
at least when you have that muscle and
it's demonstrated that you are willing
to use it when required then people will
fear you and that automatically brings
respect so now will can one person
change india if you look at the past ten
thousand years of history
if you look at the past ten thousand
years of history human history is
nothing but a sequence of great men and
women usually it's men because in the
past it was all about
brown right it was not about only
intelligence you needed intelligence but
you needed the the
muscle the masculinity in the past
because the world was a very harsh place
i suspect it may go back to that in the
future
so the thing is
the huge history of the human species is
the history of one great individual
after another
even the history of india if you look at
the people who have shaped india
in the past thousands of years of indian
history it's always been great kings and
queens
so yes to change india india is right
now a very mediocre nation unfortunately
it is a very mediocre nation with a
people who have a great amount of
greatness in them so 1.3 billion people
they all have greatness in them but they
are not aware of it
they are all the descendants of ancient
kings and queens and emperors and
empresses but they are not aware of it
they think we are all mediocre and sub
chalta hai and all that nonsense indians
today have very low standards let me
explain why we have very low standards
indians tolerate leaders who fail and
indian leaders tolerate subordinates who
fail this is called low standards
indians worship little people as heroes
right so this is the kind of nation
india is today it will take some great
individual to change the nation
a great figure so yes somebody of the
caliber of chanakya i would not talk
about hitler hitler was a monster but
somebody
of the caliber of vishnu gupta and
and someone of the caliber of
chandragupta maurya
someone of that level because india is
such a large nation india needs an
enormous a person of enormous stature
and personality and force of will to
unify the country together in the past
people ask why did the marathas not
fight with the sikhs and why did the
section fight with the marathas and why
were the british able to recruit so many
indians to fight for them against other
indians it's because indians have no
sense of unity indians have no sense of
nationality
and that's the problem so it will take
somebody with that force of character
and personality to bring india together
and make everybody see that we are all
the same people you may
bengali speak marathi you may speak
speak tamil speak
kashmiri it doesn't matter you are the
same people when someone can do that
that's when you india will unify and
become a superpower until then we are a
nation of mediocre people with very low
standards that's how it's going to go
all right
vikram somewhat i have
answered that question
rudra says in maths physics chemistry
why do we only use greek symbols even
the kovid variants are known are named
after greek alphabets oh micron
and what's special in the greek language
nothing special about the greek language
the world is eurocentric today
the people who run the world
and decide these names are all
eurocentric western oriented people and
the past 2 300 years it's we have had a
tradition tradition globally to
suppress the east to suppress the
eastern world
and to promote the greatness of the
white of the white race race and the in
the european world so it's all
eurocentrism if you look at uh
if you look at the names of the species
in biology the animal species it's all
once again
latin and greek when it comes to botany
classification of botanic botanical
species it's all latin and to some
extent greek uh the father of the
periodic table
mendeleev who was russian had named the
chemical elements
after uh with with sanskrit prefixes
aka
three that way but his work when it was
continued they discarded his
nomenclature and
and
inserted latin or greek uh
uh prefixes and and names you know so
that's what they did so dimitri
mentality was how did he get the
inspiration for the periodic table by
studying the work of
the great panini the great linguist
panini and he saw that there is so much
symmetry and order and pattern in the
patterns in the way this guy panini had
classified and organized the grammar of
the sanskrit language it was
extraordinary the way it was done and
none of us in india know this because we
don't study it right so dmitry mendeleev
was incredibly profoundly impressed with
that he was and and it made a huge
impression on him and that's when he was
uh
he was inspired to look at similar
patterns in the chemical elements and
that's how we came up with the periodic
table which is the foundation of
chemistry et cetera science today
so he used sunscreen prefixes the west
discarded it he said this stupid russian
has
done this good work but let's discard
the nomenclature that used so there is
nothing special about the greek
uh alphabet of the language nothing
whatsoever if we
had any sense of pride any sense of
being different in any sense of being a
civilization we would teach
science chemistry etc in our own
languages with sanskrit prefixes and all
that but we don't do it because we are a
nation that is completely colonized
totally from top to bottom colonized
okay
yeah no one okay let's see
okay many questions i get about the law
of attraction
uh i'm a practitioner of the law of
attraction i want to know what are your
thoughts about it and what do ancient
scriptures say about this listen i
haven't studied the law of attraction
it's not a scientific law
it is uh i think it is something to do
with spirituality or or self-improvement
you keep on focusing on good things and
you keep on um you have a goal and you
keep thinking about it like five times a
day or 20 times a day or whatever then
it you attract it towards yourself when
it comes to you listen uh there is no
scientific evidence for this but yes if
you if you program your mind to think
about a certain goal and you actually
take actions in the direction then you
may reach there certainly there is a
higher probability that you will
actually succeed so that way it will
work it won't work for everybody some
people don't have the willpower to
achieve big objectives some people don't
have the aptitude the the ability
and so it won't work for such people
some people who have that and who have
the willpower discipline to discipline
themselves it will work for them so it's
not a scientific principle it's not a
scientific law i think it is a book by
rhonda byrne i think it's called the
secret in which the law of attraction
was propounded i think
and similar uh principles or similar
ideas have been around for a long time i
haven't studied these so i cannot tell
you in detail whether it works or not
what do our ancient scriptures say about
it
uh
i i'm not quite sure if of if india's
scriptures speak about the law of
attraction or any such principle india's
scriptures are not that shallow they are
really really profound and it takes a
lifetime to to even study a small
fraction of them so
so that's what i can say about this i
get a lot of this i mean i get this
question asked a lot so i thought i'll
answer it
okay rudolph says
do you how do you understand geopolitics
that much by reading books about this
topic or just by observation and reading
history
and figuring it out yourself please
guide us under geopolitics
um
how do i understand geopolitics listen
uh since i was a kid i've been reading
about not only history but i've been
keeping in uh
keep staying on top of current affairs
i've been looking at what happens i was
interested in the second world war the
cold war i could see connections between
those two events so it's not just
history it's something that's actually
happening and the
present is
shaped by the past and therefore if you
study world history in great detail
then you will have an inherent innate
understanding
of why things are the way they are and
what the forces that shape the world the
military forces the economic forces the
political forces uh how do empires rise
and fall how do kingdoms uh become how
do how do kingdoms and cultures
disintegrate if you understand all that
you will naturally understand
geopolitics so to understand geopolitics
you have to first understand history and
not history of a small little place like
this
but the overall global history so it
takes time to develop that ability and
it's not like i read a few books i read
lots and lots of books not entire books
only the parts i found interesting and i
read lots of journal articles lots of
research papers and lots of overall
media content i am just a curious person
i read whatever i find interesting
and nowadays i even listen and i watch
things from time to time so that's how
it is
so how do you understand geopolitics you
will never ever understand geopolitics
unless you understand world history
you need to have a good understanding of
at least the past 500 years of whole is
world history not in very very
excruciatingly excruciating detail
but big picture if you understand big
picture
world history then you will get a very
good sense of geopolitics and how it
works and not just what happened what
did it happen but why things happen
why things happen what are the hidden
patterns that underlie world history and
the same patterns are at play today you
see that's how it goes so it's all about
understanding world history and
understanding the hidden patterns
that shape world history
so that's what i can say
okay um
prabal says how should what should india
do to progress
in other sports like football and how to
remove this qriket centric mentality all
it takes is investment
this sort of investment you have in the
ipl if you make the same sort of involve
investment in say football you're gonna
have a world-class league
you're gonna have a bunch of teams which
will which will necessarily want to
attract good indian talent and then
the hidden indian footballers who are
in some village or some town and who
don't have any opportunity they will all
be scouted picked up and
and elevated to the global level
it's all about investment if you invest
the same amount of money in kabaddi just
imagine what will happen it's a sport
that all the indians love actually we
get you watch it it's so interesting
it's so exciting it's a contact sport
like rugby
right you need big hefty people to do
that guys girls whatever right
so it's all about investment
right now for cricket is this big thing
but you could start a
league for kabaddi i would pay to watch
a good cupboard match i would love it i
like
sports with a little bit of contact
little bit of
a little bit of aggression i have no
issue with that and i am sure indians
also love it i mean it's it's a sport
that came out of india thousands of
years ago so cupboard d i would like to
see being promoted that way i think
there are a couple of small leagues of
kabaddi here and there and they show it
on various sports channels but i would
like to see a year-long league or at
least eight nine months long league
leave league with a few months in gray
of break to recuperate and all that
it would be so fascinating to see that
india has so much potential imagine if
india becomes gordon's board with
because of investments it's all about
investments you know i would love to see
a hockey league we had a hockey league
we may still have one but it's it's
moribund nothing is happening invest
some good money
in a hockey league india will become a
hockey super power all over again
right
it's fun sports are great to watch spend
half an hour one hour of your of your
day once once or twice a week and
watching sports it's great and it's even
great to play sports because it develops
you physically and mentally as well
it's good for personal development for
personal growth i would like to see a
mixed martial arts league in india it is
all about investment
we need entrepreneurs who invest in this
look at dana white of the ufc he started
from from scratch he started from zero
he had nothing and he built the ufc into
what it is today it's a global behemoth
so if we need indian entrepreneurs we
need indian businessmen business women
to invest in sports start up this is all
startups start up a new league of some
sport and let's see how it goes if you
do your work well if you are good at
business you're gonna make it succeed
but indian
what i see is that the the environment
isn't there in india for risk taking
people india is still a very poor nation
per capita gdp is abysmal so people are
very very afraid of taking risks you
make
you make of taking risk if you make a
mistake in business you lose your
investment you lose your money you lose
your business then it's almost
impossible to start over again in the us
it's not that way you can fail at
multiple businesses and then you can
succeed eventually because there is so
much
angel investment and all that in india
that is not there if you're in some
small village in in in bihar let's say
and you have a brilliant idea
how are you going to get the funds for
that so that is the problem in india
right now
but what needs to happen overall for
for progress in other sports is just
investments we need to put money into
that because it's going to create an
entire ecosystem in which there will be
so many jobs that are created you know
coaching jobs uh
various support staff jobs medical
sports medicine jobs coaching jobs or
stadium maintenance jobs
and an entire media industry can be
created around this it's it's
an untapped gold mine sports is an
untapped gold mine and you know what
today you wanna you wanna take a break
you have to go and switch on some tv
channel and watch cricket that's the
only option you have what if you have
seven other other sports
that you can watch it will give people
more options in life in india there are
no options that's the problem so that is
what needs to happen i would love to see
it happen when i was a kid i used to
think why don't we have these things why
don't we have a rugby league i used to
think about it because but of course
rugby is not really relevant to india
when i was a kid i used to think why
don't we have a rugby league like like
they have in other countries why don't
we have a football league why don't we
have a cricket league okay so now we
have a cricket league but we are
completely neglecting other sports
because we are still colonized this
colonial mindset play cricket
so i would like to see other sports take
off it will be great fun if that happens
great great fun
okay
peter says what is the origin of the
people of nuristan why was this region
called kafir islam before if they are
hindus why do they look european listen
what is hindu
it's not blood it's culture why do they
look european well for we have to look
into the history if you take check the
genetics of these people of chitral the
kalash people i have a video on that you
will find that they have indian origin
dna
they look whatever because they may be
living high up in the mountains so the
skin becomes fair look at me i am also
reasonably fair i don't live in the
mountains it's all genetics but we are
all the same people below the
superficial aspects that you see here
right it doesn't matter what you look
like white black brown
red eyes i mean red hair blue blue eyes
doesn't matter it doesn't matter inside
we all have the same dna if you check
the people
of this region the kalash people you
will find that their patrilineal
lineages are entirely indian
and their matrilineal lineages are more
west eurasian that's a weird mixture but
from the from the trillionaire side they
clearly have unmistakable undeniable
indian dna right
some people say they are descendants of
greeks that's why they have blonde hair
and blue eyes hey look at the greeks
today do they have blonde hair and blue
eyes no
the average greek man or woman will have
dark hair and brown eyes and reasonably
brown skin not white skin they don't
look like proper europeans so this
entire thing that they are descendants
of alexandra's soldiers is utter
nonsense right
so these are the kalash people they
practice a very old form of what we call
hinduism it is it looks like a rigvedic
form of hinduism right that's what they
practice but it's it's dying out
so in this region called which is now
known as nuristan it was called
kaphiristan in afghanistan before so i
think in the 19th century etcetera these
were people were still hindus in in see
so there are two two regions one is this
kapharistan in afghanistan or nuristan
it's called now and then there is this
region called chitra these are
essentially adjacent regions same same
overall geographical vicinity
so uh
the chitral region in pakistan these
people are still somehow
continuing the the old tradition of
ancient hinduism in afghanistan they've
all been converted to islam
so in the 19th century late 19th century
early 20th century somewhere there
these people were all massacred whoever
survived was converted by force to to
islam by the afghans and that's how
afghanistan is now entirely an islamic
country 99.9 percent so the people of
kafir islam let's let's take a look
where it is kaphiristan nuristan
let me share the screen
so we are now in the subcontinent let's
go to afghanistan and let's look at
nuristan
afghanistan
okay so this region which you can see
here is
uh nurestan so-called nuristan in
afghanistan
and
and the the the region near it is swat
chitral etc so it's all adjacent regions
right so that is where these people
lived these people uh who practiced this
ancient who had
held on to their ancestral practices
so the afghans
massacred lots of them
forcibly converted all of the rest to
islam
so
the place which was originally called
kaphiristan was then called nuristan the
land of light because islam is here now
so that's what happened that is what
happened in brief they were all
converted by force and then they said
this is the land of light now because
islam is here and hinduism is gone
so that's what happened
and why they do they look european
because of their mixed genetic status
patrilineal lineages are indian
matrilineal lineages are weirdly
west european
okay brahmagupta discovered the concept
of gravity before newtons and why is
newton created for discovering gravity
is it possible for that the concept of
gravity traveled to europe from india
see yes
the concept of gravity did originate in
india undeniable yes
what did newton do
he discovered
the inverse square law of gravitation
so that is something that wasn't there
in india all right
so he added something on top of it did
he come up with the
idea of
of gravity on his own was he inspired by
india we don't know
what we know was that there was
transmission of the uh knowledge of
calculus from india
to europe why are jesuit missionaries
who stole these ideas from india
and
then we find that calculus is certainly
discovered by two independent
european scientists one in
england newton and one in germany
leibniz in the same year
such a monumental discovery happens
independently in two places in the same
year which it doesn't which has never
happened in thousands of years before
that so it's it's ridiculous it's
obviously they both
got hold of some translations by the
jesuit priests and that's why they both
tried to claim that it was their
discovery so today
newton is credited credited with the
discovery of calculus
which is false it is now known that it
was already discovered a few centuries
ago in india maybe even before that
now gravity again we don't know if the
knowledge of gravity also traveled to
the west with these jesuit priests but
newton came up with something original
the inverse square law of gravity
which we aren't aware if any indians had
ever discovered that so it's an addition
on top of it so the foundation of the
building was clearly
built by indians and he you can say that
newton built the first floor on top of
the foundation without the foundation
the first floor would never have
happened so
that is
what it is
okay
why does the erula tribe from south
india way look different from north
indians
look be below the surface
check their dna and see
and see what it what do you see
okay let's see erola tribe dna let's
let's do a
real time search
uh one second not this
okay let's just look here
erula tribe dna what is the erula
tribe's dna
let's see if they have r1a
okay
let's search for erula i r u l a
e irula
okay this uh so yeah okay so i will have
this will take some time to research
properly so let me not
take over your time in that the thing is
this
that indians look very different
depending on what region they are in
right you go to afghanistan i'm talking
about the indian subcontinent you look
good afghanistan they look very
different from somebody in kerala or
andhra pradesh or tamil nadu or
telangana or sri lanka right
you go to balochistan they look very
different from the people of bengal
assam etc right
but if you go below the
superficial features and the color of
the skin and the color of the eyes and
hair
you go and check the dna you will find
that all indians have indian origin dna
whether it is r1a or any other
haplogroup patrilineal or matrilineal
we know that the haplogroup f
is which is an indian origin haplogroup
is the ancestral haplogroup of more than
90 percent of non-african males and
similarly the haplogroups m and n which
are matrilineal haplogroups are the
ancestral hypogroups of more than 90 of
non-african women these are also indian
origin hyper groups so people look
different it doesn't matter what you
look like you're all indians you are all
indians you're all indians you're all
indians and you are all related to each
other how many times you have to say
this i will keep on saying it and i know
i'm gonna keep getting these questions
it's fine it's fine i have no issue with
that
i heard that greeks ruled sabras region
gujarat
shed light on that
look
they were indo-greeks
okay i have already i have a video about
the indo-greeks and what it was all
about
so after the failed invasion by
alexander you had a different you had a
subsequent invasion by his general
seleucus nicator which ended up as an
indo-greek alliance he entered into a
political and familial alliance with our
emperor chandragupta maurya
maurya accepted sir lucas nikita's
daughter as his wife they became
relatives
and then seleucus nicatore went
westwards and continued his campaigns
and became a very big became the ruler
of a very big empire
to the west of india
later on his generals etc they
established small little kingdoms in
india's west india's northwest called
the indo-greek kingdoms these in these
greeks they adopted indian culture
indian lifestyle they all convert well
conversion is not the right word we have
no conversion to dharma but they all
adopted dharmic lifestyles some of them
became experts in the vedas some of them
became expert in buddhism for instance
in the buddhist precepts for instance
you have king milind who was an expert
in the buddhist precepts and also in the
vedas king million menander they call
him that was in the north west of india
and similarly it is said that one some
for some small period of time some
indo-greek kings may have ruled
in western india saurashtra gujarat you
know and these are all
not fully greek because they married
indian
ladies they all had indian wives so
their children descendants were all half
indian or one more than half indian and
half greek
so most of them eventually were just
known as yavanas or ionians greeks but
they all had indian blood and indian
culture so yes it is uh
it is believed i think it is recorded
that there was a small period of time
when saurashtra was ruled by uh was part
of the indo-greek uh kingdoms
i think junagad was known as yavanagard
for some time because it was a
city ruled by the greeks
so yes there is a short period of
history in which swarastra was ruled by
the greeks and later on it was or the
greek indo-greek era was over and then
you had the
sketian era which began again in those
keithians kitchens are the same as
indians there is no real difference and
so on so forth so
that is your answer in very brief you
can certainly look
in more detail and read up about this
matter
rita says what is a nebula is it the
birth or the death of stars crab nebula
was caused by a supernova explosion in
one one zero zero a d
a nebula is a big cloud of gas
how does the nebula form
let's let's take a look at nebulas shall
we let me show you what this is about
okay let's take a look at crab nebula
and go to images
so this is what the crab nebula looks
like
yeah it was uh
it was visible as a supernova about like
you say around 11080 or thereabouts
somewhere there
so this what you see here
is a enormous
cloud of gas
various kinds of gases and the blue
light i think comes from oxygen or
nitrogen and the different colors from
come from the ionization of different
gases
so the bluish greenish light is most
likely nitrogen and oxygen if i am not
mistaken i don't remember exactly but
that sort of thing and if you see the
same thing in different wavelengths it
looks different
all right so this may be infrared or
something and so on so so what is a
nebula it's a big cloud of gas now the
question is
how
is a nebula
formed typically a nebula is formed from
the death throes of star from a
supernova explosion sometimes you don't
even need a supernova for instance if
you have a smallish star let's say the
sun
the sun is not a big star it's it's
classified as a yellow dwarf star when
the sun reaches its old age it's in
essence it's not going to die in a
supernova it's going to die quietly
quietly no explosion no supernova it's
going to shed it's going to become a red
dwarf it's going to shed its outer
layers and eventually the outer layers
will just dissipate in
in an ever increasing
uh
in in a shell of ever increasing radius
and that will eventually become a big
nebula a big cloud of gas and what will
be left at the core where the sun is
it's going to be a white dwarf most
likely
so that is one way of forming a nebula
when a star just quietly quietly
dissipates away and then you have a big
mostly spherical nebula in the center
you have a white dwarf or something
that's left behind eventually the shape
will will change from a sphere after
many millions of years
the other way of forming a nebula is an
explosion as a stellar explosion a
supernova explosion in which a larger
star a star that's larger than the sun
dies
by exploding boom that's how it goes
so in that case you will have a nebula
that's formed by an explosion in that
case also you will have a spherical
structure but then eventually the
structure changes depending on the
ambient environment
so the crab nebula was caused by a
supernova the supernova was visible on
earth it was almost as bright as the
full moon or something in the in the in
the daytime it was visible
so that's how it is and nebulas
eventually also give birth to new stars
when the same gas etc combines with
other things and and recombines into a
star it can give birth to a new star as
well
so that is just the life cycle of stars
so i hope that explains what a nebula is
okay let's take some
more questions what do we have
um
let us see
okay her says why don't we have drawings
or formula written in our ancient texts
why did they only use words and verses
to describe all things is it because of
their higher intelligence so if you look
at the vedas the puranas these are not
scientific texts
right so there you will not find
anything mathematical or such
in the case of actual mathematical and
scientific texts you find that indians
did not use formula they encoded these
formulas in in in sanskrit
so i don't remember what exactly it is
called uh
it is a way of encoding formulae in in
in syllables and all that so it was the
indian way of doing things maybe it was
more convoluted or whatever but it was
very accurate
so you could actually
decrypt
let's see a poem it looks like a poem it
has verses in a certain meter and each
syllable
is a component of a formula so that's
how it was done that was the way of
doing things
uh so it was a little
more difficult you needed a certain
level of intelligence to even get
initiated into that so maybe it was a
way of gatekeeping that any any tom dick
and harry cannot go and do that in in
the gatekeeping was only for the level
of intelligence right
so if you are a bright enough student
you will be able to understand this and
then you will be able to use those uh
formula etc in actual scientific work
and that's how indians
understood the entire universe right
indians uh knew this
i think indians knew the speed of light
in
i think it's it's uh
it has been calculated
during the quranic era i think the speed
of light a very reasonably accurate uh
calculation of the speed of light the
value of pi was known for a very long
time the exact length of the year
right
of the year the the periods of the
various planets everything was
calculated
on the basis of laws that were encoded
of physical laws that were encoded in
mathematical formulas that were encoded
in
the syllables of sanskrit in various uh
texts
so that's just how it was done
is it higher intelligence it certainly
requires a huge amount of intelligence
to be able to do that
it was it made it hard for the lay
person to access it but maybe the lay
person doesn't need to access these
things today we had taught all kinds of
nonsense which we don't need in school i
mean does anybody use trigonometry in
their real life ever
does anyone use calculus in the real
life ever but you're forced to study
that you don't need to study it only
scientists need to know trigonometry and
calculus and algebra even even algebra
and geometry you can learn basic low
level
uh
algebra and geometry which is not bad i
mean you may use it some day in life
but
the average person never needs to use
that but we are still forced to use to
learn all that and it is a big traumatic
experience for most kids isn't it
i loved it personally but i understand
how it goes most people they they're
traumatized by this experience so the
thing is in india it was different
everybody did not have to learn this
nobody was forced to learn it only those
who were so inclined had to demonstrate
a level of intelligence where they could
do this and then they were
able to learn these things
okay uh the question is you say that out
of africa migration uh theory is the
best that we know of today yes then my
question is how did these people from
africa inhabit landmass far away far
beyond such as australia north america
etc it's called migrations
it's called migrations they migrated
there have been lots and lots and lots
of waves of migration of human beings
from one place to another even before
the out of africa migration happened
the homo sapiens
migration our ancestors migration out of
africa happened there were before that
also there were many migrations out of
africa you had the neanderthals our
close cousins
who had who were living in eurasia long
before us long before our migration
happened you had the so-called denisovan
people whose migration also happened
long before hours they also lived
i think it happened before us but they
also lived near in eurasia
uh
you know that
you have
these
fossils from indonesia from java of
hominid species that came way before us
right and it looks like there may be
evidence of human presence in
southern america that date back more
than a hundred thousand years maybe 130
000 years so if that is
proven to be true then it indicates
there was a migration out of africa even
to south america before the uh homo
sapiens migration happened 75 000 or so
years ago so how do people migrate they
take enormous risks why do they take
risks i don't know
the story is lost in time how did people
reach australia
they went by sea they they undertook a
very difficult sea voyage
i mean we know that four thousand years
ago there was the introduction of indian
genetics in the australian aboriginal
population how did these indians
from this saraswati hindu time reach
australia
right
so they undertook a very long difficult
and arduous journey humans take risks
why do they take risks the story has
been lost in time so typically you would
take a long long long journey across
land
you would take a long journey across sea
on some kind of boat or raft or
something which is able to survive the
long voyage you may get stranded
somewhere and you may set up population
there like in sentinel islands in the
andaman islands we have the natives
there who have been stranded there for
like 30 to 40 000 years right and then
you have the population of australia
which is about 50 60 000 years old
isolated population they also reached
there somehow 50 60 000 years ago they
must have undertaken a sea voyage
why do they do it we don't know but
that's just how it is and similarly uh
they say that uh in north the population
of the americas north and south americas
it is said
see let me show you the map and we will
go there
okay let's go back to maps
okay let's zoom out so
if you look at the people the native
true indigenous people of the americas
they look more like the people of
siberia and mongolia don't they if you
look at the superficial facial features
and genetically also they have been
proven to be closer
uh and related to the people of siberia
and
and mongolia etc
so if you look here
you have
the two land masses are very close by
right
it's not really far far far away and
again you have this so-called what looks
like a bridge here so in the past during
the ice ages all of this was frozen over
and you could just walk
you could just take a walk if you had
the endurance and stamina from the
eurasian land mass to the north american
landmass so it is believed
the uh mainstream theory says that there
were no human beings in the americas
until about 13 14 000 years before today
before there were no humans that's what
they claim
and these humans they migrated from
eastern asia
across the frozen uh seas
into north america and from north
america slowly slowly slowly they made
their way downwards southwards and
eventually they populated even
the southern parts of america that is
the claim that is made i think it's a
very shallow claim i think there must
have been human inhabitation in the
americas much before that and i think
the evidence is slowly emerging
so it's all about migrations it's all
about migrations humans are a migratory
species we just migrate migrate migrate
that's what we do we don't stay in one
place for too long in one human
lifestyle lifetime you may stay where
you are but when we take a bigger lens
see when we see
history from a very very narrow lens we
get a very narrow understanding of
history if you take a slightly broader
lens instead of seeing the last 50 years
see the last 300 years you will get a
better a better understanding
then if you see the last 2000 years you
get a better understanding of humanity
in the human history if you take the
last hundred thousand years you get a
big picture understanding of the
patterns of of human history and
migration
so if you look at if you take the big
picture view you find that the history
of the human species is a history of
migrations humans migrate continuously
from one place to another always in
search of better places to live better
conditions climate changes things
changes ice ages happen then you go
somewhere else
then a warm age happens the sea levels
rise then you have to go somewhere else
this happens over thousands of years
even in india we have migrations the
saraswati river dried out people moved
away from there and well elsewhere it is
known it is recorded but this happened
over thousands over hundreds of years or
or a period of 1500 years it did not
happen in one week
so that
is
the answer
okay let us see some other questions
uh mahendra says there are some concerns
over chinese electronic parts in the s
system
that would allow china to disable the
system whenever they want
could transfer of technology or buying
american systems be a better choice uh
so i am not aware of whether there are
chinese components in this
s 400 system i do not think the russians
would ever want
chinese components in something that is
essential to their defense because china
is a big geopolitical rival for them so
i am not sure if it is so then it is
surprising i would say
i thus far have never heard of any
chinese components chinese electronic
parts in this system i think the
russians would never want to would never
allow that
okay so that's point number one
transfer of technology
the russians will never transfer this
technology to any country even to the
closest allies
this is a technology that sets them
apart they will sell the system to you
they will teach you how to use it they
will give you spare parts when required
they will give you supplies of new
missiles when required but they will not
transfer the technology of how they have
built the system come on
would you
if india had developed a world-class
system
missile defense system
would it ever transfer the technology to
somebody else no matter how much money
they offered no
so we won't do that and the russians
will not transfer the technology now if
you buy buy american systems will it be
a better choice first of all the
american systems aren't as good as the
s400
they have the aegis missile defense
system that the yeah the aegis system i
think it's called the patriot uh the
evolution of the patriot missiles
but that's not as good as the
russian s400 system the s400 system is a
multi-layered missile system
multi-layered defense system it's got
like two or three comp at least three
components long range component medium
range component short range component so
for three different scenarios so you can
take care of all that it's it's a
brilliant system
the best in its class and now they are
even developing the s500 in the s550 i
think
so i think the american system will
certainly not be better than the russian
system and secondly the american system
will also have american electronic parts
which means they can disable it whenever
they want
it means the americans can also disable
it whenever they want it's called a kill
switch a kill switch
the australians
are users of american technology
american uh military technology i think
they had some one of the american
fighter planes f-16 is it
f-15a i'm not sure one of these fighter
planes and they found that when they
were using these fighter planes
it did not allow them to fire at any any
particular any specific any selected
target it would allow them to fire only
on specific targets
and the other capabilities were locked
off from them
which means the americans gave them a
weapon system which was not fully
functional it could fly do everything
but it would not fire on targets the
americans did not want to be fired at
and then the australians had to spend
several years to rewrite the entire
software package that would finally
allow them to unlock the full
capabilities of the of the of the uh
fighter aircraft so even american
systems are like that
right they want
they they can they can switch off
certain
uh capabilities when they wish remotely
so that's just how it is when you buy
arms
from a foreign
power there are always going to be these
problems and that's why i keep saying we
need to become self-sufficient in
weapons technology in the military
domain
we need to in the next 10 20 years
ensure that everything is built in-house
so that we can have the full use of all
our
assets
how do scientists determine the event
horizon is the point from which even
light cannot escape it's very simple the
calculations that come out of general
relativity the event horizon uh its
radius is 2 mg by c squared for a
non-rotating black hole for a rotating
black hole that's a different
calculation but for the standard
non-rotating black hole
with only mass and no uh and no charge
the radius of the event horizon is 2 mg
by c squared 2 m g 2 mg m is the mass g
is the gravitational constant and c is
the speed of light 2 md by c squared is
the radius of the event horizon it's all
theoretical we don't have a black hole
that we can actually test
we don't have a black hole in a lab
sitting somewhere right so it is all
theoretical we have observed objects
that look like black holes that behave
like black holes but hey
it could be something very similar to a
black hole very close to it but
something different it is very possible
so it's all theoretical thus far unless
and until we actually have a black hole
in a lab or somewhere nearby that we can
observe or unless we can actually send a
probe to an actual existing black hole
then we'll be able to actually
corroborate
what the theory says
so the event horizon right now is not
something that is observed and measured
it is something that our theory tells us
should exist so that is the boundary of
uh that is the boundary of no return the
the
the line of no written beyond that light
cannot escape from a black hole if you
go closer to the black hole than that so
that's a theoretical calculation
sunina says is there any other source of
oxygen other than plants and trees on
earth the biggest source of oxygen
is uh
is
phytophotoplankton phytoplankton it is
it is these uh
microorganisms
in the sea in the ocean
is it called photoplankton is it called
phytoplankton let me see
what is it called it is called
phytoplankton these are microscopic
algae
so when you have a pond and it turns
green
right or you have a lake and it turns
green it is these small microscopic
organisms called algae
algae can be bigger as well they can be
macroscopic as well but in the oceans
you have phytoplankton which are
microscopic algae that undergo
photosynthesis for their energy source
and they release oxygen and i think
they're they are responsible for
i believe more than half of the oxygen
that is released into the atmosphere
so
that is why the oceans are essential to
our survival if we kill the oceans we're
gonna kill the phytoplankton and then
we're gonna have a big oxygen
catastrophe so it's not just the trees
and the plants on the earth it is the
oceans and their phytoplankton that is
really vital to the survival of our
planet overall and the kind of
ecosystem we have today if the ocean
becomes anoxic
if it becomes deficient in oxygen which
can which which has happened in the past
then there is going to be an extinction
level event
and it's going to be big big big trouble
for us so that is the actually that is
actually the real major source of oxygen
the phytoplankton in the oceans
okay karan says what is hindered in
hinduism is there any difference
are they the creation of anti-hindus
what is a vyakti
it is an individual a person what is it
to be a viktor what is it
to be a human being it is viktor
what is a hindu it's a person who
practices hinduism what is it to be a
hindu it is
there is no difference
see this term hindu is now demonized
in order to to to bash hinduism
so
as of today in the academic world in the
media it is it is still wrong it is
still taboo to openly outrightly
demonize a religion so like they can't
do it to islam
till now they cannot do it to hinduism
that's why they are creating new
category or new code words for hinduism
which they can openly bash so they say
there is something called brahmanism and
they say it's different from hinduism it
is the brahminical element of hinduism
and they bash brahmanism
right the demon has brahminism
brahmanism there's no brahminism it's a
new term they've created for for just
for the purpose of of demonizing
hinduism similarly hindutva is
a proxy they use to demonize hinduism it
is again a term that has been coined
relatively recently right hindu itself
is a is a foreign term it's an exoneme
indians never call themselves hindus it
is the persians who first called indian
hindus and then the arabs doug etc
started calling indian hindus now it has
become the term only for the uh indians
who practice
indian culture the other indians who
don't practice indian culture are no
longer called hindus they are called
whatever other religion they are
so
hindutva means being a hindu
if you are a hindu you have hindu and
you that's it there is it's not a
separate form of hinduism or anything
some people define it as hinduism that
resists that stands up for itself that
could be a new way of looking at it
because most hindus are passive
and they just accept whatever happens to
them
you burn their books you destroy the
temples you enslave their temples you
steal the property and the money of the
temples hindus will just sit and watch
docile like sheep and some in those they
speak about it the protest and those are
the hindus who resist
so those are
possibly term from the hindus who
practice hindutva which means active
hinduism
you know
that sort of thing so you know these are
all it is all semantics it's all
terminology
but the term hindutva is demonized by
anti-hindus for the sake of demonizing
hinduism similarly brahmanism is a new
term they have created there is no such
thing as brahminism but today everybody
uses this term brahmanism brahmanism in
academia in the media
everywhere
they will call certain temples as
brahminical temples what the hell is
brahmanical temples these are indian
temples everybody went there so that is
all done to create more divisions in
indian society in hindu society to break
one par one component of hindus from
another
and then and create more resentment
among certain hindus
and so on to the eventual end goal is to
wipe hinduism out of the country
whatever little is left of hinduism so
that's what it is
all right where do we go
how to unite hindus leadership
leadership leadership leadership
we need the right leaders
i'm not saying we have wrong leaders i'm
not saying we have wrong leaders we need
great leaders
do rajputs and pashtuns have the same
ancestry where rajputs were one of the
militias just like the indo-iranian step
population rajputs were not mature see
this entire thing of
okay it's first of all it's a good
question i'm making a different point
which will come back to this question
all right so that this right now i see
this big fight happening
among hindus among indians
not in not hindus among indians who are
the rajputs who are the gorgeous which
who can be classified as rajputs who can
be classified as gorgeous who is higher
are rajputs higher or gorgeous higher
all this nonsense listen we are the same
people
this is all pointless
it's a waste of time
you're spending all your energy all your
efforts in fighting each other when you
should be unifying because you all have
the same blood the same ancestry it
doesn't matter who is classified under
rajput who is classified in under gurjar
who is classified under jaat
it doesn't matter
it simply doesn't matter when people try
to distort your history and portray your
your history is bad then you can fight
back against them but stop fighting
among each other this petty nonsense is
characteristic of india
india's entire vital energy is spent
fighting each other so i am just tired
of that please stop doing that those of
you who are rajputs and gurujas or or
you're confused about it it doesn't
matter i don't care i'm not going to
answer questions about drug foods and
good gorgeous right now where rajputs
lectures no rajputs were not militias
clearly they were part of the indian
society indian civilization they served
indian civilization they defended it and
they practiced uh
they were they were very they had this
big
they they were very concerned with being
virtuous
being noble
so no they were not matures there are
clearly not nature's natures are people
who have abandoned
vedic hindu practices or abundant some
aspect of the vedic practices the
rajputs were not that so they were not
lectures
see
if you look at the history of gandhar
if you look at the history of the city
of kandahar let's say kandahar then the
one of the turkic or or
persian
writers of history
more than a thousand years ago had
recorded this that
kandahar was the city of the rajputs
so it was the city of the rajputs right
and now who lives there the pashtuns
live there and who are the pashtuns they
have the same blood as this i have
demonstrated in a previous answer a few
episodes back with genetic evidence
research papers that the pashtuns are
the same as indians they have the same
genetics
right so what happened is that
north western india fell to the turks
and whoever
lived there was converted to islam
so the rajputs who lived there lost and
those who survived were voluntarily or
involuntarily converted
to islam so the pashtuns
are also a war like people they are
they were classified as a martial race i
think the british maybe not but they
have this war-like
tendency
so they are clearly the descendants of
those rajputs and the genetics as we
know are the same so it is most likely
that the pashtuns are the descendants of
the rajputs who lived in the region of
gandhar before the turkic occupation
and destruction of the region
so yes pashtuns and indians have the
same ancestry not only rajputs because
rajputs are indians rajputs have the
same ancestry as all other indians there
may be some
little bit half a person here and there
of some foreign industry which is not
relevant at all
indians have this great great fetish for
looking for foreign ancestors for for
everything i see so many who said nahi
hum indians
we are this and we are there we are gods
and we are massage or whatever are baba
the massacre are also indians
so i am just uh
there's this very big hang up for
finding some kind of foreign ancestry
everybody wants to find some foreign
industry
these foreigners also had indian
ancestry if you go back 5000 years they
also originated from from india
so it doesn't matter what ancestry you
have whether you're a rajput whether
you're a pashtun whether you are a
maratha whether you are a bengali
whether you are a tamil
it doesn't matter whether your assamese
whether kashmiri it doesn't matter you
are all indians unite unite unite wake
up
okay
my guitar nowadays oh well it's it's
somewhere here i hardly ever get to play
the guitar anymore so
i've kind of lost touch with music you
know
it's something i really enjoyed i still
enjoy it but no time
nim nirmit says
as a six how can a 16 year old student
who has very high ambitions of serving
the country mold his career in the right
proper way for the nation and the
civilization currently preparing for jee
excellent excellent very good i hope you
you succeed i wish you the best how do
you
how do you succeed for the con how do
you serve the country
as a 16 year old
you have to first develop yourself into
a substantial human being
only when you are a substantial human
being will you be able to serve the
country so right now focus on yourself i
always say this spend the first 10 20
years of your life of your adult life
spend the first 10 or 20 years of your
adult life
focusing on personal growth and
development
get good work experience
not just work experience
different industries if you can
get a lot of experience
acquire as many real-world skills as you
can and become as wealthy as you can it
is important to become wealthy because
that give that wealth will give you the
freedom to make choices later in life
so once you are 30 maybe 40 depending on
how you have progressed then you can
dedicate the rest of your life for
serving the nation because by that time
you understand how the world works
you understand how the different
industries work and you have the wealth
to make the choices that can change the
country so as a 16 year old study
acquire skills beyond your scope of
study you are preparing for iit jee yeah
that's a
that is a challenging task that you have
to prepare for the exam i don't see why
if you don't do well if you prepare
properly
and
if you get the time acquire some skills
beyond that also
today see in the 21st century it's all
about technology the people who will uh
succeed in life and the people who will
shape the course of the world are the
people the youngsters of today who are
very comfortable with high technology
and who are comfortable with learning
newer technology as it very quickly
emerges because now the new technology
doesn't emerge every 20 years now new
technology emerges every six months
so become very comfortable with
technology
high technology and you can do it for
free everything all the information all
the all the knowledge is available
online you just need to know where to
look so acquire all the skills
it is the kids of today who are going to
shape the world in the next 20 years
right so be very positive focus on
yourself focus on personal growth and
become as comfortable and confident as
possible with new emerging technology
learn technology immerse yourself in it
vr ai everything ml
gaming anime whatever interests you
do that learn that so that's what you
can do
okay let's take some other questions
lots of lots of questions let me pick
some
some questions
love with your conversation with ishkar
and watching from london we all indian
first we are we are all indian first yes
madam thank you thank you for the
comment
uh can you please throw some light on
the concept of biocentrism how much
water does this hold according to
science
i think i have the book by robert lanza
biocentrism i haven't got around to
reading it so
i think it's a theory of consciousness
that consciousness is present across the
universe or something like that you know
what uh let me read the book then get
back to you uh i have my own views about
consciousness that which may or may not
be the same as this i have
purchased the book it's lying somewhere
in one of my book shelves
i think i will read it up and then maybe
i can answer the question but it's a
interesting concept it's all about
consciousness
and the
vedic view is that consciousness
permeates the universe it's not just
something that arises
arises in in living beings
maybe it concentrates itself in certain
areas like a human brain or something
but it's something that's
present to some extent across the
universe so that is a vedic view of
consciousness i'm not sure if robert
lanza has the same view i will have to
see it but a good question and i will
certainly at some point return to this
question
james rafi says please make video on
astrophysics love from bangladesh love
you back sir i am a big friend of
everyone from bangladesh you are our
people
we are the same people so yes i will
make videos on astrophysics and thank
you for the comment thank you for
watching appreciate it
okay
why are indian aspirants still preparing
for the upsc ias exam which is one of
the toughest exams in the world when we
know when we all know
that
they will all go ahead and do corruption
okay good question see
let's take the corruption thing aside
for just a minute
why are indian aspirants still preparing
for the upsc ias exam see
look at india today big picture india is
a nation with a very low per capita gdp
it's it's officially a poor nation
people have very few opportunities
we still don't have the
booming startup ecosystem that everybody
will get a job whether
no matter what is their level of
education and
ability everybody will have job that
still isn't there right so job security
is a very big problem
now indian parents
by nature are risk others they want you
to keep your head down don't take any
risks take the safest path path become
secure in life get a stable job get
married have kids and then repeat the
process all over again that is something
that has come to us over the past 1000
years of foreign occupation just survive
survive somehow survive
and i don't blame indian parents for
this
now what is the safest path in the
country
it's a government job if you have a
government job you have a job for life
you will never be sacked no matter how
badly you manage things
you will never be sacked you have a job
for life if it's a government job
or an academic job professors teachers
lecturers
sweepers
no i don't know sweepers but yeah most
of them have jobs for life once you are
in you're in
right
so ias upsc it is a job that is going to
be a job for life and after you retire
you will have a pension for life
that is the safest option in the world
that's why so many indians want to get
into this and of course so i think that
explains why so many people want this
they want to get into the big
bureaucratic machinery of india and then
they will be sitting there
relaxing
for the rest of their life chai pio
right
okay i'm not saying all bureaucrats are
like that but the vast majority are like
that
so um and do they do corruption yes of
course we know that i mean that's an
undeniable fact there is a great deal of
corruption
someone said that
what is wallab by patel who said that
the bureaucracy is the steel frame of
india well the steel frame is rotten
sorry
you know so yes there is a great deal of
corruption i hope that someday india
will launch a war on corruption where is
the war on corruption if you want india
to have better days
there needs to be a significant
concerted and a real
real war on corruption not some fake
things here and there
so corruption is a very big problem it
is one of the biggest things that's
holding india back
yeah so
yeah that's all i can say
okay
the full truth is veganism good
it's a personal choice uh in the indian
world view in indian civilization in
indian dharma
vegetarianism is regarded as the highest
ideal yes it is it is regarded as the
superior way of living
but we know that indians have
always some indians not all
i think the majority of indians at any
given point in time before the invasions
before the foreign occupation before
that time the majority of indians would
have practiced vegetarianism
there would always have been some
indians who were non-vegetarian
especially the so-called martial races
the people who had to go to war who
needed extra protein to bulk up
physically
and even then you know
you can get all the protein you require
from vegetarian food
so i would say that vegetarianism
i'm not talking about veganism i'm
talking about vegetarianism
vegetarianism is certainly
a healthier lifestyle
it is certainly a better lifestyle it is
better for the environment for the
planet
so yes it is good veganism takes it to
an extreme in which there is no dairy
products also that's a personal thing
it's a personal choice it is a new fad
that has emerged in the west we will not
eat any animal product i don't care
about what they do i do not take i do
not regard the west as a valid
uh
as a place from which we need to take
our influences
we succeeded in the past with our own
methodology with our own civilization
with our own culture we just need to
look back to the time when we were
successful what lifestyles did we have
at the time
what and then we can
we can
try to replicate that
and in our personal day-to-day lifestyle
and that can help us
get better and get ahead in life so
typically indians were vegetarian not
vegan
not vegan
so is veganism good well it's a personal
choice
there is no animal product involved in
veganism in vegetarianism you can
consume milk
and you can consume things like cottage
cheese paneer right paneer etc so those
things are allowed in vegetarianism in
veganism you cut even that out in which
case you lose a significant source of
protein you can still gain protein from
pulses from legumes etc you can
certainly be a completely vegan person
and become a bodybuilder no doubt about
it so it's a personal choice but i would
say that vegetarianism is a superior way
of life not just for yourself for
ourselves but also for the planet
okay i have spoken many times about the
multiverse there is
no evidence for it
did emperor chandragupta maurya
was a jain monk see chandragupta maurya
uh
in the end stage of his life
he adopted the jain
philosophy the jaina way of living
and he um
he abdica so before he he did that he
abdicated the throne
in favor of his son
and his son became the emperor of india
and chandragupta maurya said i am done
with this life he went down south in the
southern part of india i think it was in
karnataka
over there he started practicing jain
precepts
and he starved himself he fasted himself
to death
it's called saleh khanna or something in
in the jaina practices i am not an
expert i apologize if i have
mispronounced it in any way whatsoever
but it is the uh
one of the ways in which certain jain
people choose to leave the world
to fast themselves out of this physical
existence so typically it would take 40
50 days of starving no eating only water
i suppose i think i'm not sure
so that is what chandragupta maury did
he was done with his service of the
nation he went to the south of india
there he adopted jain practices and he
fasted himself until he was no longer
present on this planet physically
consciously right so that's what i did
so he did not live a giant life he was
an orphan boy chandragupta mori was an
orphan boy who was brought out of
uh obscurity and
by the great vishnu gupta chanakya
and he was a
he was
uplifted
or promoted you could say to the status
of the emperor of all india
of the majority of most of the indian
subcontinent most of it right so he did
not leave a jaina life it's only after
he abdicated from the throne you could
say he retired from his position as
emperor that's when he adopted jain
principles jane precepts the jain
lifestyle so once again jainism is not a
separate religion
today everybody is so
badly brainwashed hinduism is a separate
thing sikhism is a separate thing
jainism is a separate thing buddhism is
a separate thing these are all
part of dharma
these are different ways of living
different ways of looking at the world
but the core values are all the same
there is no difference there are more
similarities than differences the
differences will be two or three percent
the similarities are 99 90 98 99
97 if i'm saying three percent so stop
looking at the small minute differences
the similarities are what matter you
know what happens
so i i hope i've answered about
chandragupta maurya
you know what happens let me let me
explain something bigger
see when you go to school
what are you rewarded for
you your reward is the marks you get in
an exam right
you may have multiple exams during a
year term exams
and then you have the big final year
exam
and what are you rewarded for what are
you punished for let's let's take a look
at that
in an exam
you may have studied the topic well
let's say you're talking about talking
about history let's say you are talking
about some chapter of history
when you write the essay in the exam
about the to answer the question about
whatever part of history is asked over
there if you make the smallest mistake
let's say instead of one zero six six
eighty you say one zero six seven eighty
they will cut two marks
if you
write the spelling of a name of a king
slightly long
instead of chandragupta you will say
chandragupta then they will cut two
marks again so because because of these
extremely small minute minor in
insignificant mistakes you lose a lot of
marks
right so you are trained since your
childhood to focus on the very small
things
it doesn't matter if you have got the
big picture the real idea or not but you
only want to make sure that you don't
get the small things wrong and that
happens from first standard second third
third standard 10th standard 12th
standard college university onwards your
entire childhood you are trained to
focus on the small minor insignificant
details
and that's why indians are always
fighting over small things that's why
indians can never see the big picture
the education system is ruining
the country
it is ruining the children of the
country
all you focus on hey you are wrong you
made this spelling wrong hey you are
wrong you got this wrong array you got
the big answer right did you see that no
it doesn't matter that's why everybody
in the comments says hey you got this
wrong no you made this wrong you said
this wrong
look at the big picture small little
mistakes here and there do not matter
and similarly when it comes to dharmic
precepts the small insignificant
differences between hinduism jainism
buddhism sikhism are immaterial they all
have the same value system they all have
the same principles the same concepts
the same precepts the same tradition it
is the same thing
look at the big picture you have now you
have been taught to look at the small
things thus far now please listen to me
and try to start looking at the bigger
picture it will take time to change the
mindset but you will not succeed in life
unless you also understand the big
picture because the big picture is the
real picture the small picture is only
going to confuse you always
look at the big picture you will never
be confused
okay that was a long
rant let me not do that again
okay where are we
reservations rishabh says is there a
need for reservations in india if yes
then how long should it be continued in
our country you know reservations is not
a bad thing it is implemented in a
terrible way
it is implemented on the base on the
basis of the british imposed caste
system four divisions right
and then you have these different uh
subdivisions of scs and st scheduled
tribes and all that for instance you
have these people
what are they called
they're called the cookie people
the cookie people in northeast of india
who are recent immigrants from burma
right
now they are given the status of st
actually they're not even indians now
they are given the status of indians
they are given citizenship their
citizenship
they are they were people who were
expelled from burma in very recent times
and they came into india as
as migrants
it may have happened before 1947 but
that doesn't change anything
right
but now they are given the status of st
i think and they get all kinds of
privileges that normal people don't get
so what happens is that we have we are
giving reservations
on the basis
of so-called hereditary castes which
were created by the british by the
british bureaucracy
now there are so many people in various
in every so-called caste you have very
prosperous people very rich people and
very poor people
which means that there are people who
are really rich who get privileges that
they don't need but they take it and
people and other so-called castes who
may be really poor who may be destitute
will not get any of that privilege
so this is implemented in a terrible way
and now it's become the one of the major
components of politics if anybody tries
to remove the reservation system they're
going to lose an election so
unfortunately because of this
sad reality every political party has to
pander to caste
and to reservations
what should be done actually what should
have been done
reservations should have been given on
the basis of financial status
if you come from a poor family if you
don't have funds then you should be
given free education
that's it
free education and maybe free or free
medical treatment that's it
and then it all once you have free
education and free medical uh treatment
etc or let's say some free food from
time to time
then you have all the means at your
disposal to succeed in life
and then there should be no
uh reservations and admissions because
you gave
free education to those who are
financially uh not in a good good
situation
so reservations should only be on the
basis of financial status not on the
basis of caste or whatever the hell else
there is
and reservation should be
in education
until the lower and middle education
like up to 10th 12th standard after that
whatever your academic performance is
that should be the only
sole basis for admission into higher
education college university etc so that
gives everybody the same
level playing field
when there are students
that's how it should be implemented but
today we have reservations in everything
in government sector in in iits in
colleges in universities in government
jobs they some people are trying to push
reservations even into the private
sector which will completely ruin india
so reservations are not a bad thing but
they have to be implemented
properly on the basis of financial
condition no matter what so-called caste
you're from
if you are financially
poor
you should be given free education
and whatever else should be given that
is the fair way of doing it i don't
think anybody should have an objection
to that
right
and again that should only be continued
as long as india is a poor country once
india becomes middle incarnation there
should be no reservation as long as
everybody is reasonably uh prosperous
all right let's take some other
questions um
did ancient indians have any contact
with the native americans and native
australians we have no evidence for
native americans but like i have
explained indians had contact with the
native australians today's native
australians indigenous australians have
a significant not a significant but a
non-insignificant amount of indian dna
so you can look at my previous answers
and you will get the details
okay okay okay let's see more questions
how much knowledge did we lose in the
books that were burnt in the ancient
universities almost all of our knowledge
all of the records of the distant past
so that's why we lost so much and that's
why they said that indians are people
who don't record history in the written
form which is a lie but yeah
we lost
all our knowledge the library is burnt
for months so you can imagine how many
millions and millions of ancient
manuscripts were destroyed i would say
more than 95 of the knowledge would have
been destroyed in that whatever is left
maybe about 5 10 at most and that too is
lying and crumbling
the asi is supposed to safeguard those
manuscripts to digitize them nothing is
happening they are lying in some dusty
corner crumbling into dust and that is
the status of the asi in the government
of india which simply doesn't care about
india's incredibly rich heritage
i heard about this
north korea bans laughter and leisure
activities for 11 days on the death
anniversary of its previous dictator
awesome what can i say it must be fun to
be a north korean
how can we change the constitution what
are the ways i you know what i am not an
expert in indian law indian constitution
all that stuff
maybe uh
so i cannot say for sure i i get the
feeling it is not possible to change it
through the constitutional means
uh recently we know that uh prime
minister modi i mean
in the first term he tried to build
bring about some reforms in the way the
judges were appointed and the judges
threw it out
the constitution was amended
i think it was called the njac or
something
the entire process was done a small
amendment in the constitution and the
judiciary threw it out
they threw out the will of the people of
india
so it is very hard to make any changes
in this system
i is there a mechanism to change the
entire constitution and bring and throw
this one out and bring in a new one i
don't know maybe i should talk to a
legal expert and maybe i should have a
discussion with somebody who understands
these things so
maybe something for the future
all
right let's see some more questions
uh bhakti moment i am not a specialist
in that i have never found it very
interesting
apologies to anybody who finds it
interesting i did not find it
interesting
okay so this is the question could you
talk about the bhakti movement of india
specifically the contribution of
shankaracharya ramanujacharya and
madhavacharya
not my specialty this is not something i
have studied in detail i am saying this
honestly i have not studied this in
detail
so i am
today december 19 2021
not the right person to answer this
maybe two three months down the line i
may be the right person if i read about
this so let's see
maybe it is an important chapter in
india history during the foreign
occupation
maybe it contributed something to the
survival of india's
civilization and culture
so
i will read about this
and in a future episode please ask me
again or if i remember i will do it
myself and i will answer this question
but thank you for the question it is
certainly a good question
difference between yadu and shiraj puts
any others no idea
no interest in this i am tired of these
little differences
they are the same people
that's all i care about
do we have any other questions that are
fascinating
was the andaman and nicobar islands
always part of india you know
in the past
indian civilization was spread all the
way to the philippines
right
see india is not a nation state
once again we look at things from a
certain perspective from a narrow
perspective nation state everything is
nation nation nation in the past there
were no nations
there were no nations before the treaty
of westphalia uh two three hundred years
ago
this is a new european system that has
been implemented
nations with clear defined political
boundaries and passports and visas in
the past there was no such thing
in the past you could just walk
or sit on a horse sit on a camel sit on
a donkey if you wish they're on a zebra
and travel
and as long as you were a respectable
individual and you had good intentions
you had a clear stated purpose that i am
traveling to so traveling to so-and-so
place i'm passing through people would
not stop you though there was no visa
there was no passport you could just
travel as long as you were a respectable
individual and you had a clear purpose
today because the west stole all the
wealth from the east that's why they
have created all these restrictions on
travel because they don't want the
easterner easterners the poor people of
today whose wealth has been stolen to
come into the west of course now there
is a certain kind of immigration
happening only a certain kind of
immigration which they are engineering
right now which is a different story so
in the past we did not have these nation
states
india was sometimes an enormous
unified empire sometimes it was a
combination a collection of smaller
kingdoms but it was always one
civilization india is a civilizational
entity india is a civilization state
and in the past the civilization state
extended all the way to the philippines
it incorporate included
present-day burma
thailand malaysia indonesia
cambodia laos vietnam philippines
yunnan the so-called yunnan province of
china even china and japan and korea
because it was all part of the same
civilizational umbrella
so were the undercover pi islands part
of this of course they were part of this
of course there is no question about it
it is our possession it is our territory
and it has historically
always mean ours
okay what else do we have
did our vedic ancestors acquire most of
the knowledge by practicing dhyana and
especially by consuming psychedelics
should it be allowed to be used by
today's generation
psychedelics
are a shortcut
they give you some visions and
hallucinations in some experiences
as a shortcut
but you don't know what to make of it
you don't know what to make of it
i have never consumed any of what what
is it called
ayahuasca lsd whatever these are
psychedelics yeah so uh i personally
have no experience of that but
some people do that i have nothing
against that
our ancestors did not acquire all this
knowledge by consuming psychedelics and
getting some random visions and random
experiences
their
practice was focused there was no
shortcut to it it took years it's called
dhyana yes you're right it's called
dhyana that is how all this enormous
corpus
of knowledge of literature of philosophy
of science of spirituality
and much more was developed through
dhyana
through dhyana that is a grueling
form of meditation it takes years it is
frustrating if anybody has tried it they
know it's frustrating in the beginning
it takes a long long period of
perseverance and dedication and
willpower to make a breakthrough and
then it gets easier
yeah so that's what dhyana is
diana is it's especially useful for uh
understanding the inner universe because
it is said that the inner inner universe
is in tune with the outer universe
and that's how you get insights into the
nature of the universe into the physical
laws into the
metaphysical laws and much more so
that's how our ancients our ancestors
came up with all this enormous corpus of
knowledge over thousands of years it was
all built upon the foundations created
by the predecessors or preceding
generations and that's what was
destroyed in the fires in the
destruction of the libraries and
universities a thousand years ago by the
turks
it's a crime against humanity what was
done so that is how this knowledge was
uh acquired
discovered right not by consuming
psychedelics there are certain uh
certain uh
paths
which are called the left hand parts
right the the certain sadhus agorys etc
they do consume certain psychedelics i
think it's uh
it is marijuana ganja they call it ganja
character which are plant products these
are not
refined
uh narcotics these are plant products
right that's what they consume
so uh that is the practice among certain
parts in certain sadhus etc who still do
it today maybe it was a tradition that
went back a long long time it is
possible
so they have their own path of doing
things they want to attain personal
liberation personal moksha or personal
enlightenment in some way
but i don't think they they create the
they have those paths
people belonging to those parts have
created all the knowledge right it is
the dhyana people who have created the
knowledge now should psychedelics be
allowed
by in in to be used by today's
generation
so first of all
i am against the consumption of any
substance that is harmful to health
because it's going to
create problems in society if you have a
higher incidence of cancer for instance
it's not good for society
people who smoke
are prone to cancer people who chew pan
tobacco are prone to getting terrible
disfiguring tumors and they may lose
their life because of that so that is
bad but that is allowed
that is allowed
legally and i think uh in india things
like
marijuana or band are they
marijuana and and
charis which is again
the resin of the same plant i think all
that is banned the question is
is it more harmful than tobacco i think
it's less harmful than tobacco i have
heard that the ganja
and and charas are not even habit
forming to a large extent at least to
the extent that tobacco is tobacco is
extremely habit-forming
and
they
so they don't have the harmful effects
that tobacco has
so i don't see why it is something that
is banned it has been part of india's
culture for centuries for thousands of
years it's even part of india's
celebrations so i think this is a stupid
move to ban these elements of indian
culture it is just blindly aping the
west india's government in the past
[Laughter]
has been full of mentally colonized
people
who think that whatever the west does is
the right thing we should just blindly
like a monkey copy copy what they're
doing so i think that's why india banned
the consumption of uh the use of of
ganja and and chorus i think
i see nothing wrong if some people want
to do that
is it is it
is it a crime is there a victim
somewhere it's it's called a victimless
crime you do something which is against
the law but there are no victims you're
not harming anyone so i think india
needs to revisit these things
i know the in practice it is not really
implemented people i think they
use it in festivals and all that right
during holi or whatever other festival
the
people do use these products and i don't
think anybody cares the police doesn't
really interfere most mostly
so i think it is implemented very
largely but we need to remove these
stupid provisions from india's law you
know
so i i think as far as it's not some
horrible narcotic like heroin cocaine or
or whatever else is there crystal meth
as long as it's not those things
i think society
the the legal system should should not
interfere too much there is too much
paternalism that we the legislators know
what is best for you you are little
children who don't understand anything
we know what's best for you and we'll
tell you what to do that attitude needs
to go
the legislators are not some gods
they are not some superior human beings
they are simply the representatives of
the people of india and they need to
remember that
so this needs to change you know india
needs to change in this manner
okay let's take a couple of more
questions
this is an interesting question so i
don't have an answer but see is is
konkani older than marathi
where did the konkani people originate
so this is a fascinating question and
why hasn't any god damned historian in
maharashtra and konkan answer these
questions
i assure you
that you ask any historian any official
historian in a university they will give
you some random answer they don't have
the answers
the konkani prakrit and marathi
maharashtri prakrit
may have the same origin because
to an untrained year
when you hear konkani and when you hear
marathi they sound pretty much
similar
there is clearly differences in the two
languages but there is more similarity
than there are differences
right so i think there is clearly a
a common origin maybe there was an older
prakrit that gave birth to both these
languages
so the prakrits are languages that are
upper branch languages that
are descendants of
panini and sanskrit
so konkani and marathi i think are
closely aligned closely allied closely
related
languages
and they
i am pretty certain they have the same
origin where did the konkani people
originate well konkan is in
southwestern india
north
of kerala
north of karnataka i would say yeah
southern part of maharashtra goa that
that region is konkan
where did the people see all the people
of india have the same origin we are all
the descendants of the ancient vedic
people of india
afterwards there were migrations
internally within india after the drying
up of the great river the great mother
river saraswati people travelled here
and there up and down
but everybody has the same roots the
great chatrapati
shivaji maharaj
he was a descendant of the rajputs of
of rajasthan it is well known
there is a clear connection between him
a familial connection
between him and maharana pratap
so he is a maharashtrian he is the
greatest
he is the
one king the people of maharashtra and
much of india revere because of his
great actions
one of the greatest kings of india in
the past 1000 years
well he is a he was a maharashtrian he
was a maratha but he was a descendant of
rajputs
so we are all interrelated
the question is valid i don't have the
answer you will need a historian who
specializes in small regions of india to
get the answer for this i am i have
always been a big picture historian i
can give you a big picture answer
i get many of the questions and i really
appreciate the questions you know i get
these questions
where did the people of garwal originate
where did the karwali language originate
where did the people of kuwait originate
from these small regions i unfortunately
am not an expert in these topics
so i cannot answer the these questions i
can give you a bigger
bigger picture answer from from a larger
perspective but i think you need to uh
perhaps
go to your local university ask a
historian and see if that guy or lady
has the answer for you
and you know that's what i can say
all right all right
why don't you try for kbc could easily
win one crore listen i have no interest
in kbc
no interest whatsoever
but yeah thank you
for the suggestion
okay let us take one final question for
today this is a question
many people ask me
tell us about secret societies like
illuminati
and freemasons how does it affect the
modern world
okay so the illuminati are a
hypothetical society there is no
evidence for that if it exists it's a
completely secret society
okay so
if you talk about the illuminati some
people will accuse you of indulging in
conspiracy theories which i
don't
entirely agree with so illuminati is
just hypothesis there is no actual
evidence of their existence but many
people believe in the existence of a
certain power structure
that controls the entire world and
that's called the illuminati
right
the freemasons are not
that secret society they actually do
exist
so let's take a look at the free
missions who are the freemasons right
let's go here and let's search for
freemasons
so the freemasons are another secret
society
okay
that are present across the world it it
originated several centuries ago
and they are now openly out there in the
world they have their lodges and
chapters worldwide let's see india
freemasons india
the grand lodge of india
there is the website called the grand
lodge of india so we have indian
freemasons too and they openly say they
are freemasons but they will the thing
about the freemasons is that they don't
disclose the real objectives what is the
objective and purpose of the of the
society of freemasons what is the true
purpose that is never revealed they say
our purpose is to create a better
society and to instill the the
principles of leadership and being a
good father good friend good head of
family etc into people and all that but
there is a secret purpose which is never
revealed
and let's see about let's take a look at
the freemasons of india so there's a
website called the grand lodge of india
if it will
load one second let me
i'm
okay there is this website called the
grand lodge of india
look at the freemasons look at the
members
so it's a secret society which has its
origins
in
the abrahamic religions
judaism and christianity most likely
judaism it has a secret purpose
a secret western purpose not an indian
purpose it is not an indian society it's
a foreign society see the members of the
society
rudyard kipling
surprise my dear friends
surprise
behold
swami vivekananda
jrd tata
and so it continues
so this is a secret society
whose true purpose we don't know i'm not
saying it's good or bad or whatever
but look at the individuals who are a
part of that
it has nothing to do with indian culture
indian civilization indian national
interest
look at the people who are who were
members of that society
i'm just showing you facts
rudyard kipling
for instance
he was introduced into the society by a
member of the brahma samaj i'm not i
don't remember who it was was it was it
ramon roy was it someone else it means
the brahmos this fellow rahm mohan roy
he also may have had ties with this i'm
not sure
i will have to look it up
but rudyard kipling was introduced
initiated into the society by a member
of the brahma-samaj an indian
rudyard kipling was a british poet
writer
born in bombay mumbai
so he was initiated into that by a
member of the brahma samaj you had
people like swami vivekananda who were
members of the society
tata motilal nehru and many other people
and we don't know what is the secret
purpose of the society
that is all i can tell you did you learn
something new today i think at least if
you are a curious person inquisitive
person you would want to take this
information i just showed to you the
facts i just showed you and
look a little deeper
into the true uh
true
nature of the society and
the association of certain prominent
individuals with the society what was
the real purpose what is the need to be
in the society
that's all i can say
okay brothers and sisters ladies and
gentlemen
i am done for today
thank you very much for your questions
so two more sessions left in this year
we will do that and then we will welcome
the new year
take care my friends and i will see you
very soon bye